[Music]
about one in four women will eventually
suffer from fibroids most commonly
manifesting is excessively heavy periods
and pain or pressure
why might you feel pressure
because you may be carrying around 26
pounds of tumors in your uterus
fibroids are the most common reason
women get hysterectomies having their
uterus removed completely a major
surgery associated with disability and
death
but all surgery carries risk and the
chances of dying within a month of
surgery may only be about one in twelve
hundred
which makes it among our safest
surgeries safer than getting your
gallbladder removed for example
but of course you lose the ability to
bear children and costs billions of
dollars a year
yet despite the high prevalence
significant pain and suffering and huge
economic impact relatively little is
understood about the cause and disease
process that lead to fibroid tumors
avoiding atomic bomb blasts whenever you
can it's probably a good idea in terms
of decreasing fibroids risk
what about more easily modifiable risk
factors well alcohol consumption is
associated with increased risk
particularly beer
and whenever you hear that whenever you
hear beer specifically you think of the
hormonal effects specific to beer
specifically the the powerful
phytoestrogen found in hops
well if that phytoestrogen is increasing
fibroids risk what about the
phytoestrogens in soy
well this was looked at in the black
women's health study fibroids are two to
three times more prevalent among
african-american women so they thought
maybe dairy intake might be contributing
to the disparity
given their higher levels of lactose
intolerance and indeed dairy consumption
was associated with reduced risk
they figured it was the calcium content
or maybe the vitamin d but perhaps the
women were drinking soy milk instead and
that was increasing their risk
no a soy intake was found to be
unrelated the same finding in a group of
predominantly white women
though they didn't note a protective
association with the amount of lignans
flowing through their bodies
lignans are another class of
phytoestrogens found predominantly in
flax seeds but throughout the plant
kingdom
hard to make any generalizations about
soy phytoestrogens though as soy
consumption was rather low across the
board this was done in washington state
if you go to japan where they have the
highest per capita soy consumption in
the world you get a bigger spread of
intakes
the researchers had previously found
that soy intake was inversely associated
with risk of hysterectomy meaning women
who ate more soy had lower hysterectomy
rates suggesting potentially protective
effect of soy against uterine fibroids
since that's the main reason women have
their uterus removed
this would be consistent with in vitro
studies that found that the main soy
phytoestrogen seemed to inhibit fibroid
tissue proliferation in a petri dish
but when they specifically looked there
was no evidence of a link to soy at all
protective or otherwise
the same was found in one study out of
china fruit and vegetable intake was
associated with significantly lower risk
of fibroids but soy food consumption was
not
but a second study out of china
published the same year found a
significant association between soy milk
intake and fibroids
that's consistent with the three
alarming case reports of women with
symptomatic fibroids reporting an
unusually high intake of soy milk or
regularly consuming excessive amounts of
soy or extremely high intakes of soy
every day for decades
it's hard to take these cases seriously
when nowhere do they actually say how
much they were consuming
the only quantitative mention was 40
grams of isoflavones which roughly
translates to 400 gallons of soy milk
every day
that would be excessive
but also impossible
the only way to know for sure is to put
it to the test not just a population
study or anecdotal reports but
randomized women to two years of soy
phytoestrogens the amount found in three
to five cups of soy milk a day and
no significant effect on the frequency
or growth of fibroids was found
[Music]
foreign